<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>John A. Bernau</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on John A. Bernau</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Read Generalist Journals?</title>
      <link>/blog/generalist-journals/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/generalist-journals/</guid>
      <description>Word Count: 1340 Sociology is a broad discipline. As the general “social science” it overlaps considerably with history, anthropology, political science, and economics, not to mention African American Studies, Women’s Gender and Sexuality Studies, Communication Studies, et al. While some see this breadth as a positive attribute, the dangers of a fragmented discipline are hard to ignore. For example, as Stinchcombe (2001) argues, sociologists do not agree on the appropriate subject matter nor the way to measure it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digital Humanities Fellowship at Emory’s Center for Digital Scholarship</title>
      <link>/blog/ecds_fellowship/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/ecds_fellowship/</guid>
      <description>This week I am excited to start my new position as the Digital Humanities Fellow at the Emory Center for Digital Scholarship (ECDS). The center offers a touch-point for faculty and students working on a variety of digital projects, from interactive web design and online publication to the basics of working with video, photography, and audio in an academic setting. ECDS also partners with various academic departments, agencies, and faculty members to produce original scholarship.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Exploration: Global Trends in Extreme Poverty</title>
      <link>/code/wb_poverty/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/code/wb_poverty/</guid>
      <description>In this post I perform some data exploration in R. I’ll cover the following topics:
 Importing data Preparing data Merging data Plotting data Appendix: A 10-line code summary  More specifically, I’ll be using the World Bank data on extreme poverty to plot global trends of 162 countries between 1977 to 2016. While sociologists talk about inequality at length, it’s useful to remember the state of poverty on a global perspective.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AJS - Vol. 123 No. 4 - January 2018</title>
      <link>/blog/ajs_v123n4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/ajs_v123n4/</guid>
      <description>Craciun, Mariana. 2017. “Emotions and Knowledge in Expert Work: A Comparison of Two Psychotherapies.” American Journal of Sociology 123(4):959–1003.
Summary: The author uses ethnographic data to examine the role of emotions in the work of psychoanalysis (PA) and cognitive-behavioral (CB) therapy. She proposes a model of emotions as supportive, didactic, and inductive (an “affective-relational framework”). While both therapies use emotions, PA knowledge and/or findings don&amp;rsquo;t translate well outside their discipline (i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>REVIEW: The Marriage-Go-Round by Andrew Cherlin (2010)</title>
      <link>/blog/cherlin2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/cherlin2010/</guid>
      <description>Cherlin, Andrew J. 2010. The Marriage-Go-Round: The State of Marriage and the Family in America Today. New York, N.Y: Vintage.
 Word Count: 1981 The Marriage-Go-Round is an outstanding example of sociological scholarship. Andrew Cherlin combines history, theory, and data to provide a thorough understanding of marriage as an organizing force of American social life. Beginning in colonial America of the 17th century, the book follows the institution of marriage through its turbulent ride to the present.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>REVIEW: Ethics in an Age of Self-Interest by Peter Singer (1993)</title>
      <link>/blog/singer1993/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/singer1993/</guid>
      <description>Singer, Peter. 1993. How Are We to Live?: Ethics in an Age of Self-Interest. Amherst, N.Y: Prometheus Books.
 Word Count: 1929 “Is there still anything to live for? Is anything worth pursuing, apart from money, love, and caring for one’s own family? Is so, what could it be?” Like any prospective reader, I was drawn in. Who doesn’t want a philosophically sound argument for how to live one’s life?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2018 Martin Levin ICPSR Training Award</title>
      <link>/blog/levin_icpsr_award/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/levin_icpsr_award/</guid>
      <description>Last week I was honored to receive the Martin Levin ICPSR Training Award at our annual Sociology Department awards ceremony. Marty Levin was a faculty member in the Emory University Sociology Department for many years, playing a key role in the methodological and statistical training of graduate students. Marty also served on the Board of Governors of ICPSR (Inter-University Consortium for Political and Social Research). This award will give me the opportunity to attend a workshop over the summer and learn new methodologies for the statistical analysis of text as data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Exploration: Empty Pews in U.S. Congregations</title>
      <link>/code/empty_pews/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/code/empty_pews/</guid>
      <description>This post offers an example of data exploration in R. I’ll cover the following topics:
 Importing data Preparing data Plotting data v.1 Standardizing Variables Plotting data v.2 APPENDIX: Creating smooth animations  More specifically, I’ll be using the US Congregational Life Survey from the ARDA data archives, to examine how has American church attendance fluctuated between 2001 - 2008. This issue is important to any longitudinal understanding of religiosity, and American religiosity in particular has been the subject of much debate (Berger et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>I am a PhD candidate in the Department of Sociology at Emory University. I study how groups use language to solve social problems. My previous research has examined (1) how modern states differ in their public interpretations of national disasters, and (2) how country musicians use linguistic codes to signal group membership. In my dissertation (3) I develop a method for anchoring multiple word embedding spaces using the cosine similarity of target words.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Code</title>
      <link>/xcode/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/xcode/</guid>
      <description>2018
 Data Exploration: Global Trends in Extreme Poverty
  2017
 Data Exploration: Where Do American Baptists Live?
 Data Visualization in R: Part 4 - Text Labels, Faceting, Editing Themes
 Data Visualization in R: Part 3 - Other Geoms (lines, bars, box, violin, density)
 Data Visualization in R: Part 2 - Assigning Variables to Attributes
 Data Visualization in R: Part 1 - Getting Started  Copyright &amp;copy; 2018 John A.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Code</title>
      <link>/xcode/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/xcode/</guid>
      <description>2018
 Data Exploration: Global Trends in Extreme Poverty
  2017
 Data Exploration: Where Do American Baptists Live?
 Data Visualization in R: Part 4 - Text Labels, Faceting, Editing Themes
 Data Visualization in R: Part 3 - Other Geoms (lines, bars, box, violin, density)
 Data Visualization in R: Part 2 - Assigning Variables to Attributes
 Data Visualization in R: Part 1 - Getting Started  Copyright &amp;copy; 2018 John A.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Exploration: Where Do American Baptists Live?</title>
      <link>/code/baylor/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/code/baylor/</guid>
      <description>In this post, I’ll be using R to download, clean, and plot some basic information about the regional concentration of American denominations using the Baylor Religion Survey of 2010.
To begin, make sure to load a few basic packages.
require(&amp;quot;tidyverse&amp;quot;) require(&amp;quot;foreign&amp;quot;) require(&amp;quot;psych&amp;quot;) require(&amp;quot;car&amp;quot;) require(&amp;quot;RColorBrewer&amp;quot;) The dataset I will be using comes from the 2010 Baylor Religion Survey (2010), a nationally representative survey of more than 1,500 American adults. It’s hosted on The Association of Religion Data Archives (ARDA).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DataViz in R: Part 1</title>
      <link>/code/dataviz1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/code/dataviz1/</guid>
      <description>These materials come from an interactive workshop I lead at the Emory Center for Digital Scholarship.
Part 1 includes:
1. Orientation to RStudio
2. Basics of ggplot
3. Changing size, shape, and alpha (opacity)
4. Three ways of specifying color
5. Putting it all together
6. Exercises 1 and 2
1. Orientation to RStudio  If you are new to R or RStudio, there are a lot of introductory courses and materials online.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DataViz in R: Part 2</title>
      <link>/code/dataviz2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/code/dataviz2/</guid>
      <description>These materials come from an interactive workshop I lead at the Emory Center for Digital Scholarship.
Part 2 includes:
1. Assigning variables to graphical parameters
2. Expressing variables using color
3. Putting it all together
4. Exercises 3 and 4
# install.packages(&amp;quot;psych&amp;quot;) require(&amp;quot;psych&amp;quot;) # install.packages(&amp;quot;ggplot2&amp;quot;) require(&amp;quot;ggplot2&amp;quot;) # install.packages(&amp;quot;RColorBrewer&amp;quot;) require(&amp;quot;RColorBrewer&amp;quot;) 1. Assigning variables to graphic parameters In part 1 we learned how to set the global options for many parameters such as size, shape, opacity, and color.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DataViz in R: Part 3</title>
      <link>/code/dataviz3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/code/dataviz3/</guid>
      <description>These materials come from an interactive workshop I lead at the Emory Center for Digital Scholarship.
Part 3 includes:
1. Line graphs
2. Bar graphs / Histograms
3. Other geoms
4. Combining geoms
5. Exercise 5
# install.packages(&amp;quot;psych&amp;quot;) require(&amp;quot;psych&amp;quot;) # install.packages(&amp;quot;ggplot2&amp;quot;) require(&amp;quot;ggplot2&amp;quot;) # install.packages(&amp;quot;RColorBrewer&amp;quot;) require(&amp;quot;RColorBrewer&amp;quot;) # install.packages(&amp;quot;dplyr&amp;quot;) require(&amp;quot;dplyr&amp;quot;) 1. Line Graphs In part 1 and 2 we’ve been working with scatterplots, and here I’ll briefly introduce some of the other options.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DataViz in R: Part 4</title>
      <link>/code/dataviz4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/code/dataviz4/</guid>
      <description>These materials come from an interactive workshop I lead at the Emory Center for Digital Scholarship.
Part 4 includes:
1. Adding text labels
2. Facet wrap / grid
3. Editing theme elements
4. Exercise 6, 7, 8
# install.packages(&amp;quot;psych&amp;quot;) require(&amp;quot;psych&amp;quot;) # install.packages(&amp;quot;ggplot2&amp;quot;) require(&amp;quot;ggplot2&amp;quot;) # install.packages(&amp;quot;RColorBrewer&amp;quot;) require(&amp;quot;RColorBrewer&amp;quot;) # install.packages(&amp;quot;dplyr&amp;quot;) require(&amp;quot;dplyr&amp;quot;) 1. Adding Text Labels When adding text to a plot, geom_text works like many other geoms in ggplot. Below, using the mpg dataset, we’ve taken a scatterplot of fuel efficiency and added labels to show the manufacturer of each vehicle.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meta-Sounds in Modern Country Music: Lyrical Intertextuality as Boundary Work 1989-2014</title>
      <link>/research/country-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/country-music/</guid>
      <description>John A. Bernau
ABSTRACT: This article examines how artistic communities use linguistic codes to signal group membership and police boundaries. Specifically, I examine the contemporary rise of self-reflexive intertextuality in modern country music: songs about specific styles of music consumption, other canonical artists, or “country music” itself. I argue this can be understood as a response to increased genre fuzziness and rising demographic diversity among country audiences. Using an original dataset of 27,682 songs from 1989-2014, I employ dictionary-based computational text analysis to examine this theme over time and in relation to a variety of factors, include artist gender, career status, commercial success, linguistic repetition, and political environment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/xresearch/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/xresearch/</guid>
      <description> Publications Under Review
 June 2018 - Meta-Sounds in Modern Country Music
 March 2018 - How Do Modern States Culturally Respond to Disasters?  Manuscripts in Progress
 Sad Songs &amp;amp; Waltzes: Country Music Sentiment and Chart Performance
  Dissertation Research
 The (De)Institutionalization of Kübler-Ross&amp;rsquo;s Five-Stage Model of Death and Dying   Copyright &amp;copy; 2018 John A. Bernau </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SOC 333 Sociology of Religion</title>
      <link>/teaching/sor/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/teaching/sor/</guid>
      <description>Syllabus PDF
This course offers an introduction to the sociological study of religion. As a discipline, sociology blends theory, history, and carefully collected data to better understand social phenomenon. This perspective offers the best chance at understanding the complex phenomenon we know as religion.  We will look at classical theorists like Karl Marx, Emile Durkheim, and Max Weber to see if their 150-year-old ideas can help us understand religion today: Would Karl Marx and MLK get along?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching</title>
      <link>/xteaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/xteaching/</guid>
      <description>Independently Taught Courses:
SOC 333: Sociology of Religion
Workshop Author / Leader:
Data Visualization in R
Data Cleaning and Manipulation in R
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;(co-led with Megan Slemons)
Zotero for Academic Research and Publishing
Proposed Courses:
SOC XXX: Applied Statistics for Social Scientists
SOC XXX: Sociology of Death and Dying
SOC XXX: Philosophical Roots of Sociological Thought
Served as Teaching Assistant:
SOC 506: Applied Regression (Graduate-level)
SOC 389: Cont. Chinese Culture</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Website!</title>
      <link>/blog/new-website/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/new-website/</guid>
      <description>My new website is up! It is built by Hugo and deployed through Netlify. A huge thanks to Yihui Xie and colleagues for the blogdown package in R and the many helpful tutorials on getting started (like this one). For general R / data / blogging inspiration, check out Julia Silge’s and David Robinson’s websites, as well as the editorial team at The Pudding who put together beautiful data-visualization-driven essays. Lastly, a major shout-out to my friend and colleague Trent Ryan for general R support and encouragement (and help with the cocoa theme!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Sympathetic Leviathan: How Do Modern States Culturally Respond to Disasters</title>
      <link>/research/sympathetic-leviathan/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2018 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/research/sympathetic-leviathan/</guid>
      <description>Bin Xu &amp;amp; John A. Bernau
ABSTRACT: While events are central to the sociology of the state, natural disasters, a type of events with substantive and theoretical significance, have received scant attention. To address this gap, we theorize states’ cultural response to disasters—how states use discourses and actions to address moral and political meanings of death and suffering. We borrow insights from a few strands of scholarship: the sociology of disaster, cultural sociology of the state, and cultural theories of trauma and theodicy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/private/dan_gtdemo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/private/dan_gtdemo/</guid>
      <description>Google Trends Dan Demo, August 2018
There is an R package that allows you to directly import GoogleTrend data. You specify 1) search terms, 2) geographic region, and 3) time span. You can search one word or multiple-word phrases by combining with “+”. They have region codes at most levels you could want: global, country, state, city, metropolitan area, etc. At the widest, time span can go from 2004-present. At the shortest, you can pull trends from the last hour!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overlapping Shootings</title>
      <link>/private/gtdemo2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/private/gtdemo2/</guid>
      <description>In a 30-day window there are 37 events that have some degree of overlap:  {&#34;x&#34;:{&#34;data&#34;:[{&#34;x&#34;:[15540,15541,15542,15543,15544,15545,15546,15547,15548,15549,15550,15551,15552,15553,15554,15555,15556,15557,15558,15559,15560,15561,15562,15563,15564,15565,15566,15567,15568,15569,15570,15571],&#34;y&#34;:[2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2,2],&#34;text&#34;:[&#34;id: 41
total_victims: 82
date3: 2012-07-19
id: 41
case: Aurora theater shooting&#34;,&#34;id: 41
total_victims: 82
date3: 2012-07-20
id: 41
case: Aurora theater shooting&#34;,&#34;id: 41
total_victims: 82
date3: 2012-07-21
id: 41
case: Aurora theater shooting&#34;,&#34;id: 41
total_victims: 82
date3: 2012-07-22
id: 41
case: Aurora theater shooting&#34;,&#34;id: 41
total_victims: 82
date3: 2012-07-23</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>